<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Monolith on Chandan Kumar Dash</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/monolith/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Monolith on Chandan Kumar Dash</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/monolith/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
            <title>Understanding Monolithic Architecture: The &#39;All-in-One&#39; Approach</title>
            <link>http://localhost:1313/blogs/understanding-monolithic-architecture-the-all-in-one-approach/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>http://localhost:1313/blogs/understanding-monolithic-architecture-the-all-in-one-approach/</guid>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;In the world of software architecture, &amp;ldquo;Monolithic&amp;rdquo; often gets a bad rap, associated with &amp;ldquo;legacy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;old-school&amp;rdquo; code. But the truth is, &lt;strong&gt;Monolithic Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; is the foundation upon which many of today&amp;rsquo;s tech giants were built. It remains the most practical choice for many new projects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post breaks down what Monolithic Architecture really is, its core components, and why you might—or might not—want to use it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-monolithic-architecture&#34;&gt;What is Monolithic Architecture?&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monolithic Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; is a unified model for designing a software application. In this approach, the application is built as a &lt;strong&gt;single, indivisible unit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Think of it like a massive Lego castle where every brick is glued together. You can&amp;rsquo;t just take off a tower and replace it without potentially affecting the stability of the entire structure.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-unified-concept&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Unified&amp;rdquo; Concept&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a typical web application, you have three main layers:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frontend&lt;/strong&gt;: The User Interface (UI).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backend&lt;/strong&gt;: The Business Logic.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Layer&lt;/strong&gt;: The Database interface.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a Monolith, all these layers are managed within a &lt;strong&gt;single codebase&lt;/strong&gt; and deployed as a &lt;strong&gt;single executable&lt;/strong&gt;. Even if the database itself runs on a separate server (like a managed PostgreSQL instance), the &lt;em&gt;code&lt;/em&gt; that interacts with it is tightly bundled with the business logic and API endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;characteristics-of-a-monolith&#34;&gt;Characteristics of a Monolith&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Single Codebase&lt;/strong&gt;: All features (User Auth, Payments, Inventory) live in one Git repository.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unified Deployment&lt;/strong&gt;: To update one line of code, you must redeploy the entire application.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shared Memory&lt;/strong&gt;: Components can call each other directly (function calls) rather than over a network (API calls), making communication extremely fast.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;advantages-why-start-with-a-monolith&#34;&gt;Advantages: Why Start with a Monolith?&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplicity&lt;/strong&gt;: It&amp;rsquo;s much easier to develop, test, and deploy one application than twenty microservices. &amp;ldquo;git push heroku master&amp;rdquo; is the epitome of Monolithic simplicity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower Latency&lt;/strong&gt;: Communication between modules happens in-memory. There&amp;rsquo;s no network overhead of serializing JSON and making HTTP requests between services.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easier Debugging&lt;/strong&gt;: You can trace a request from start to finish in a single IDE window. No need for complex distributed tracing tools.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistency&lt;/strong&gt;: It&amp;rsquo;s easier to enforce code standards and transactional integrity (ACID) when everything shares the same database.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;disadvantages-the-growing-pains&#34;&gt;Disadvantages: The Growing Pains&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tight Coupling&lt;/strong&gt;: A bug in the &amp;ldquo;Recommendations&amp;rdquo; module could crash the entire application, including &amp;ldquo;Checkout&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalability Issues&lt;/strong&gt;: You can&amp;rsquo;t scale just the &amp;ldquo;Video Processing&amp;rdquo; part of your app. You have to scale the &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; monolith, which wastes resources.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dependency Hell&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;: Updating a library for one module might break another module that relies on an older version.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slow Build &amp;amp; Deploy&lt;/strong&gt;: As the codebase grows to millions of lines, compiling and deploying can take upwards of 30-40 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;real-life-examples&#34;&gt;Real-Life Examples&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-the-startup-mvp-most-common&#34;&gt;1. The Startup MVP (Most Common)&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost every successful startup—&lt;strong&gt;Airbnb, Uber, Instagram&lt;/strong&gt;—started as a Monolith.&#xA;Why? Because when you are validating a product, speed of iteration is everything. The overhead of managing microservices slows you down.&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Example&lt;/em&gt;: A simple E-commerce store built with &lt;strong&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Django&lt;/strong&gt;. The storefront, admin panel, and payment processing are all in one app.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-stack-overflow-the-majestic-monolith&#34;&gt;2. Stack Overflow (The Majestic Monolith)&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the highest-traffic sites on the internet, runs on a monolithic architecture (.NET). They prove that with proper optimization (caching, efficient DB queries), a monolith can scale to handle billions of requests. They didn&amp;rsquo;t need microservices to succeed; they needed good engineering.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-shopify-modular-monolith&#34;&gt;3. Shopify (Modular Monolith)&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shopify&lt;/strong&gt; is another giant that famously stuck with a monolith for a long time. They eventually evolved into a &lt;strong&gt;Modular Monolith&lt;/strong&gt;—where the code is still in one repo and deploys together, but the internal boundaries are strictly enforced to prevent &amp;ldquo;spaghetti code.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-monolith-or-not&#34;&gt;Conclusion: Monolith or Not?&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose a Monolith if:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You are a startup or building an MVP.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Your team is small (e.g., &amp;lt; 10 developers).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You want to focus on business features, not infrastructure complexity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider Distributed/Microservices if:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You have large, independent teams that need to deploy separately.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Specific parts of your app need independent scaling (e.g., video encoding).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The monolith has become too large to build and test efficiently.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Monolithic Architecture is not &amp;ldquo;outdated&amp;rdquo;—it&amp;rsquo;s a valid, powerful design choice. The key is knowing when it fits your needs and when it&amp;rsquo;s time to break it apart.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
        </item></channel>
</rss>
